This little choke point is called the
Bab al-Mandab or Gate of Tears.
It used to be nothing but a recipe for
shipwrecks.
>> [music]
>> It was known mostly for strong winds,
unpredictable crosscurrents, and shallow
reefs that made navigating it dangerous.
And it wasn't very valuable because if
you go through it, you just end up in
the Red Sea, which was a dead end for
most of history. That is until a French
company miraculously cut a canal through
this part of Egypt and changed the world
forever, nearly halving the time that it
would take for Europeans to get to Asia,
where they were all racing each other to
conquer, colonize, and bring back
unfathomable wealth to their countries.
The Suez Canal was a massive upgrade to
this hunt for resources. So, now you
have a new front in this race, a
scramble for control over this new route
to Asia. This windy little choke point
was no longer just the Gate of Tears. It
was an important bit of water, one of
the most important on Earth, at least
for the empires. They had to keep an eye
on it. So, the British take this little
island right at the choke point. They
put a lighthouse on it.
>> [music]
>> They also take control of a port just
south of the choke point. The Italians
then show up and purchase this bit of
coastline from local sultans, eventually
taking over this whole stretch of coast
called Eritrea. And the French would
start fixating on this strip of sparsely
populated coast right on the banks of
the choke point, the land that would
become Djibouti. The sultans here told
the French that yes, they could have a
bit of this newly strategic land in
exchange for protection. The locals here
knew what was going on. The great
empires were all scrambling and racing,
and they were going to use their prime
real estate to get what they wanted, to
leverage the situation. Smart. So, the
French set up their colony, they call it
Côte française des Somalis or French
Somaliland. This choke point would
become a key base for projecting power
and refueling on their way to carve up
and plunder Asia.
>> [music]
>> France would hold on to their little
colonial invention for a long time. Even
as the world would decolonize after
World War II, France held on to this
strategic colony along the choke point.
Until eventually, the locals rose up,
there were protests, they clashed with
the local authorities, and it led to an
independence vote. And in 1977, Djibouti
became a new country.
>> [music]